Guide to the Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Oral History Collection on the Transport Workers Union of America OH.011
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Oral History Collection on the Transport Workers Union of America
1984-1998
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
OH.011
1 Linear Feet in 1 cassette box and 1 shared media box.
32 audiocassettes
24 sound discs (cd)
The Transport Workers Union (TWU) was founded in 1934 and represented transportation workers in both the public and private sectors. TWU's New York City-based Local 100 was its largest branch, which encompassed transit workers in the subway and bus systems, as well as private bus and taxi companies. The collection consists of interviews with officers, members, and staff of the Transport Workers Union. Subjects discussed mainly concern TWU history in the New York City area, but there are some references to union politics and activity on the national level. The collection also includes an audio recording of TWU songs.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was created for the Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives by Brenda Parnes, Joe Doyle, and Gail Malmgreen in 1985. The accession number associated with this collection is 1985.006.
Arrangement
Interviews are arranged alphabetically by the intervewee's last name.
Historical Note
The Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Oral History Collection on the Transport Workers Union of America was initiated by Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives staff member Brenda Parnes in 1985 to fill gaps in documentation as she processed the papers of the union. The interviews were conducted by Parnes and Joseph Doyle from 1986-1988, then continued by Gail Malmgreen from 1990.
The Transport Workers Union (TWU) was founded in 1934 by Irish immigrants and represented transportation workers in both the public and private sectors. By 1950, the TWU had organized transit workers throughout the nation and had chartered more than 100 Locals. TWU's New York City-based Local 100 was its largest branch, which encompassed transit workers in the subway and bus systems, as well as private bus and taxi companies.
Union President Mike Quill was influential in the union's activities from his election in 1935 until his death in 1966. In 1948, Quill and the union broke ties with the Communist Party of the United States of America, and communists were excluded from union membership thereafter.
In the 1950s, the TWU was active in organizing for rail transport and airlines workers, as well as the civil rights struggles within the Southern labor movement. The TWU was the only international to hold out against the merger of the CIO with the AFL in 1955. In 1966, the union organized a transit strike and President Mike Quill passed away shortly after.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of interviews with officers, members, and staff of the Transport Workers Union, including Shirley Garry Quill, Maurice Forge, and Gerald O'Reilly. The subject matter mainly concerns TWU history in the New York City area, but there are some references to union politics and activity on the national level. The collection also includes an audio recording of TWU songs.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Access to some audiovisual materials in this collection is available through digitized access copies. Researchers may view an item's original container, but the media themselves are not available for playback because of preservation concerns. Materials that have already been digitized are noted in the collection's finding aid and can be requested in our reading room. If you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives, special.collections@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596 with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Custodial History
In 2014, interviews with Ira Coleman-Polansky and Walter Nelson were removed from the collection. Coleman-Polansky's interview is present in the Oral History of the American Left Collection (OH.002) and the Communist Party of the United States of America Records (TAM.132). Walter Nelson's transcribed interview was outside of the scope of this collection.
Related Materials
Transport Workers Union, Local 100: S. Goldstein Interviews (OH.047) includes interview session notes for Gerald O'Reilly and possibly other materials related to the OH.011 interviews.
Other collections related to the Transport Workers Union include:
Transport Workers Union of America: Records of Locals (WAG.234).
Transport Workers Union of America Records (WAG.235).
Maurice Forge Papers (WAG.106).
Gerald O'Reilly Papers (WAG.105).
Transport Workers Union, Local 100: Joseph Gayol Files (WAG.085).
Transport Workers Union, Local 100: Naomi Allen Files (WAG.295).
Transport Workers Union of America, Executive Board Minutes, 1938-1971 (Microfilm, Reel 7452).
Transport Workers Union of America, Scrapbooks, 1933-1949 (Microfilm, Reels 7453/1-11).
Transport Workers Union of America and Shirley Quill Photographs (PHOTOS.032).
Separated Materials
Two audiotapes, "Martin Luther King Jr. Speech at Constitutional Convention of TWU," were moved to WAG.235 in July, 2022.
Transport workers -- Labor unions -- New York (State) -- New York -- History.; Transport workers -- Labor unions -- United States; Collective bargaining -- Transport workers -- United States.; Irish Americans -- New York (N.Y.); Quill, Mike, 1905-1966; Transport Workers Union of America. Local 100; Transport Workers Union of America
- Victor and Sonia Bloswick, Feb 26, 1984; cuid1034 (Box 1, Audiocassette 011_001, 011_002)
- John Burnell, Nov 17, 1986; cuid1035 (Box 1, Audiocassette 011_003, 011_004)
- James Connolly Memorial, Undated; cuid1036 (Box 1, Audiocassette 011_055, 011_056)
- Eladio Diaz, 1982
- Maurice Forge, Oct 17, 1986 - May 10, 1987; cuid845 (Box 1, Audiocassette 011_005, 011_006, 011_007, 011_008, 011_009, 011_010, 011_011, Box Shared Tamiment 122, Cd 011_035, 011_036, 011_037, 011_038, 011_039, 011_040, 011_041)
- Joseph Kutch, Jul 26, 1998; cuid1037 (Box 1, Audiocassette 011_012)
- Alan Lawrence, Jun 10, 1986 (Box 1, Audiocassette 011_013, 011_014, Box Shared Tamiment 122, Cd 011_033, 011_034)
- Joe McCarthy, Nov 5, 1986 and Dec 1, 1986; cuid1038 (Box 1, Audiocassette 011_015)
- John and Sandra O'Brien, Apr 26, 1988; cuid1039 (Box 1, Audiocassette 011_016)
- Gerald O'Reilly, Jun 9, 1982 and Feb 3, 1987; cuid846 (Box 1, Audiocassette 011_017, 011_018, 011_019, Box Shared Tamiment 122, Cd 011_042, 011_043, 011_044)
  Scope and Content Note
  Interview includes discussion of time off, 1926 strikes, brotherhood, and the IRA.
- Armando Ortiz, Jul 26, 1990 (Box 1, Audiocassette 011_020, 011_021, 011_022, 011_023, Box Shared Tamiment 122, Cd 011_045, 011_046, 011_047)
- Shirley Quill, Sep 22, 1986 - Jan 20, 1987; cuid847 (Box 1, Audiocassette 011_024, 011_025, 011_026, 011_027, 011_028, 011_029, Box Shared Tamiment 122, Cd 011_048, 011_049, 011_050, 011_051, 011_052, 011_053, 011_054)
- Pat Reilly, Dec 15, 1986; cuid1040 (Box 1, Audiocassette 011_030)
- Anna Rose, Mar 1, 1988; cuid848 (Box 1, Audiocassette 011_031, Box Shared Tamiment 122, Cd 011_056)
- TWU Songs, Undated; cuid849 (Box 1, Audiocassette 011_032, Box Shared Tamiment 122, Cd 011_057)
  Scope and Contents
  Content is a series of songs; both side 1 and side 2 of original cassette end with a fade out in the middle of a song.